"Is Breakfast the Most Important Meal for
Weight Loss or Should It Be Skipped?"
Breakfast iswidely touted as not only
the most important meal of the day
in general, but specifically
in relation to weight loss.
This is not just a pop culture
prescription from
checkout aisle magazines,
but an idea put forward by
prestigious institutions such as
Johns Hopkins, NYU, Mayo Clinic, even
the United States Surgeon General.
"Want to trim your waist?"
read a headline
from the American
Dietetic Association.
"Try eating breakfast,"
referring to breakfast
as perhaps the best kept
weight-trimming secret.
But is it true?
The Duke School of Medicine's
health newsletter was skeptical:
"It's always been billed as the most
important meal of the day—until now."
While it's widely presumed that eating
breakfast protects against obesity,
the belief is held up as a poster child of
biased distortion of the scientific record.
No one can argue that
there isn't an association
between body weight
and breakfast.
Studies have shown that obesity
and breakfast skipping tend
to go together beyond a shadow
of a doubt, in fact gratuitously so.
By 1998 we already had what might
be considered strong evidence
of an association between
breakfast skipping and obesity,
but researchers continued to repeat such
studies to the point of ridiculousness.
This meta-analysis found that by 2011,
the combined P value had reached 10-42.
OK, what does that mean?
Why is that ridiculous?
In science, P value refers to the chance
of getting a result that extreme
if in fact there really
was no such effect.
How small a chance is 10-42?
This is how small that number is.
In other words, the probability
that the association between
obesity and breakfast
skipping was just a fluke
is less than the chances of winning the
lottery, not once but five times in a row,
and then subsequently getting
struck and killed by lightning.
OK, so the association between
breakfast skipping and obesity
is indeed beyond question.
We know the association is true.
People who skip breakfast are
more likely to be overweight;
that's beyond a shadow of a doubt.
The question, though, is whether
that iron-clad relationship
between breakfast skipping and
obesity is actually cause-and-effect.
To illustrate the difference
between correlation and causation,
let me share an example of
the manipulation of science
by the candy industry.
The National Confectioner's
Association had the gall
to warn parents that restricting candy
may make their children fat.
They justify this outlandish claim with
this study, that they funded of course,
that showed that candy consuming
children and adolescents
were significantly less likely
to be overweight and obese.
The industry-funded researchers go
on to imply that this exonerates candy.
But what's more likely?
That cutting down on
candy led to obesity,
or rather that obesity led to
the cutting down on candy?
In other words, the lower candy
consumption may reflect
the consequences of
obesity, not the cause,
as parents of obese
children try to restrict treats.
Similarly, the finding that those who
skip breakfast tend to be heavier
is equivalent to saying those who
are heavier tend to skip breakfast.
Doesn't it seem more likely
that overweight individuals
might just be skipping breakfast
in an effort to eat less,
rather than eating fewer meals
somehow leading to weight gain?
Now it's possible that skipping breakfast
could slow your metabolism
or cause you to overeat so much later
in the day that you'd gain weight,
but you can't know for sure
until you put it to the test.
Sometimes, randomized controlled trials
are infeasible, impossible, or unethical.
To test to see if parachutes save lives,
you can't exactly boot half the
people off a plane without them.
But you could easily randomize people to
eat breakfast or not to see what happens.
And it turns out eating breakfast does
not seem to affect your metabolism rate
or sufficiently suppress your appetite.
Most studies—95%—found that
eating breakfast tends to lead
to the same or greater
caloric intake over the day.
Even when people ate more at
lunch after skipping breakfast,
they didn't tend to eat an entire
breakfast worth of calories more,
and so ended up eating
fewer calories overall.
For example, feed people about
a 500-calorie breakfast,
and at lunch they may eat
about 150 calories less
than those randomized to skip
breakfast, but they would still end up
with about a 350-calorie surplus
over the breakfast skippers.
Does this then translate
into weight gain over time?
Researchers at Brigham Young University
randomized 49 women who habitually
skipped breakfast to either start eating
breakfast or continue skipping.
If breakfast somehow
magically leads to weight loss,
then the newly eating breakfast
group should benefit.
But no, compared to those who
continued to skip breakfast,
adding the extra meal led to hundreds
more daily calories consumed
and nearly a half pound
of weight gain a week.
If you already eat breakfast and start
skipping it, will you lose weight?
We'll find out next.
Where did this whole
breakfast-is-the-most-important-meal-
of-the-day concept come from?
The father of public relations,
Edward Bernays, infamous for his
"Torches of Freedom" campaign to get
women to start smoking back in the 1920s,
was paid by a bacon company
to popularize the emblematic
bacon and eggs breakfast.
The role of public relations, he wrote
in his book entitled "Propaganda,"
is the conscious and intelligent
manipulation of the organized
habits and opinions of the masses.
Public relations specialists thereby
constitute an invisible government,
the true ruling power of our country.
Breakfast is big business. Powerful
corporate interests such as the breakfast
cereal lobby are blamed for perpetuating
myths about the importance of breakfast.
This editorial in The American Journal
of Clinical Nutrition urged nutrition
scientists to speak truth to power
and challenge conventional wisdom
when necessary even when
it looks like we are taking away
motherhood and apple pie.
Actually, the editorial concludes,
reducing the portion size of apple pie
might not be a bad idea, either.
So, should we break the feast
and skip breakfast to lose weight?
Though advice to eliminate breakfast will
surely pit nutrition scientists against
the very strong and powerful
food industry, skipping breakfast
has been described as a
straightforward and feasible strategy
to reduce daily calorie intake.
Unfortunately, it doesn't seem to work.
Most randomized controlled studies
of breakfast skipping found
no weight loss benefit
to omitting breakfast.
How is it possible if skipping breakfast
means skipping calories?
The Bath Breakfast Project—
a famous series of experiments
run not out of the tub, but the
University of Bath in the UK—
discovered a key to the mystery.
Men and women randomized
to either eat breakfast—
defined as taking in at least
700 calories before 11am—
or fast until noon every day.
As in similar trials, the breakfast
eating group ate a little less throughout
the rest of the day, but still ended up
with hundreds of excess daily calories
over the breakfast skippers.
Those who ate breakfast consumed
more than 500 calories a day more.
I mean, over six weeks that would
add up to over 20,000 extra calories.
Yet after six weeks both groups ended up
with the exact same change in body fat.
Wait! How could tens of thousands of
calories just effectively disappear?
If more calories were going in
with no change in weight,
then there must have been more
calories going out. And indeed,
the breakfast group was found to
spontaneously engage in more kind
of light-intensity physical
activity in the mornings
than the breakfast skipping group.
Light intensity activities include things
like casual walking, light housecleaning
activities, not structured exercise
per se, but apparently enough
extra activity to use up the bulk
of those excess breakfast calories.
There's a popular misconception that our
body goes into energy conservation mode
when we skip breakfast by
slowing our metabolic rate.
That does not appear to be true,
but maybe our body does intuitively
slow us down in other ways.
When we skip breakfast
our body just doesn't seem to
want to move around as much.
The extra activity didn't completely
make up for the added calories though.
We seem to still be missing
about 100 daily calories,
suggesting there may be another
factor to account for the mystery
of the MIA morning calories.
Recent breakthroughs in
the field of chronobiology—
the study of our body's natural rhythms—
have unsettled an even more sacred cow
of nutrition dogma: the concept
that a calorie is a calorie.
It's not just what we eat,
but when we eat.
Same number of calories, different
weight loss, depending on meal timing.
Just to give you a taste, the exact same
number of calories at breakfast are
significantly less fattening than
the same number of calories
eaten at supper. What?
That's just mind-blowing.
A diet with a bigger breakfast
causes more weight loss
than the same diet with a bigger dinner.
Because of our circadian rhythms,
morning calories don't appear to
count as much as evening calories.
So maybe breakfast should indeed be the
most important meal of the day after all.